This is the Large Hadron Collider.
هذا مصادم الجسيمات الكبير.
It's 27 kilometers in circumference.
محيطه 27 كيلومتر؛
It's the biggest scientific experiment ever attempted.
إنه أكبر تجربة علمية تتم محاولتها على الإطلاق.
Over 10,000 physicists and engineers
أكثر من 10,000 من علماء الفيزياء والمهندسين
from 85 countries around the world
من 85 بلداً من جميع أنحاء العالم
have come together over several decades
قدموا معاً على مدى عدة عقود
to build this machine.
لبناء هذه الآلة.
What we do is we accelerate protons --
ما نفعله هوأننا نقوم بتعجيل البروتونات --
so, hydrogen nuclei --
لذلك ، نواة الهيدروجين --
around 99.999999
حوالي 99.999999
percent the speed of light.
في المئة من سرعة الضوء.
Right? At that speed, they go around
حسناً؟ في تلك السرعة، و يدورون
that 27 kilometers 11,000 times a second.
11,000مرة فى الثانية على ذلك القطر الذى مساحته 27 كيلومتر.
And we collide them with another beam of protons
ونقوم بصدمها بشعاع آخر من البروتونات
going in the opposite direction.
يسير في الإتجاه المعاكس.
We collide them inside giant detectors.
نقوم بصدمها داخل كاشفات عملاقة.
They're essentially digital cameras.
هي كاميرات رقمية في الأساس.
And this is the one that I work on, ATLAS.
وهذا هو الذي أعمل عليه فى تجربة أطلس.
You get some sense of the size --
يمكنك الإحساس بالحجم --
you can just see these EU standard-size
بالنظر للناس بحجم معايير الإتحاد الأوروبي
people underneath.
تحت الرسم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You get some sense of the size: 44 meters wide,
يمكنك الحصول على بعض الإحساس بالحجم: 44 متر للعرض،
22 meters in diameter, 7,000 tons.
بقطر 22 متر، 7,000 طن.
And we re-create the conditions that were present
وسنقوم بإعادة تهيئة الظروف التي كانت موجودة
less than a billionth of a second after the universe began
بأقل من المليار من الثانية بعد بدأ الكون --
up to 600 million times a second
تصل إلى 600 مليون مرة في الثانية
inside that detector -- immense numbers.
داخل هذا الكاشف -- أعداد هائلة.
And if you see those metal bits there --
وإذا كنتم ترون هذه القطع المعدنية الممغنطة هناك --
those are huge magnets that bend
تلك الهائلة هى التي تغير مسار
electrically charged particles,
الجزيئات المشحونة كهربيا،
so it can measure how fast they're traveling.
بحيث يمكن قياس مدى سرعة ترحالها.
This is a picture about a year ago.
هذه الصورة قبل نحو سنة.
Those magnets are in there.
تلك المغناطيسات بالداخل هناك.
And, again, a EU standard-size, real person,
ومرة أخرى، شخص حقيقي بحجم معايير الإتحاد الأوروبي
so you get some sense of the scale.
حتى تحصلوا على بعض الإحساس بالمقياس.
And it's in there that those mini-Big Bangs will be created,
وهناك تلك الإنفجارات العظيمة المصغرة سيتم إنشاؤها،
sometime in the summer this year.
في وقت ما في صيف هذا العام.
And actually, this morning, I got an email
وفي الواقع، هذا الصباح، تلقيت رسالة بالبريد الإلكتروني
saying that we've just finished, today,
تقول بأننا قد إنتهينا، اليوم،
building the last piece of ATLAS.
من بناء آخر قطعة من تجربة أطلس.
So as of today, it's finished. I'd like to say
إذاً إعتباراً من اليوم، إنتهت. أود القول بأن
that I planned that for TED,
و هذا ما خططت له لـ TED !
but I didn't. So it's been completed as of today.
لكننى لم أفعل. إذاً فقد تم الانتهاء إعتباراً من اليوم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Yeah, it's a wonderful achievement.
نعم، إنه إنجاز رائع.
So, you might be asking, "Why?
إذاً، قد تتسألون "لماذا؟
Why create the conditions that were present
لماذا خلق الظروف التي كانت موجودة
less than a billionth of a second after the universe began?"
بأقل من بليون من الثانية بعد بدأ الكون؟"
Well, particle physicists are nothing if not ambitious.
حسناً، علماء فيزياء الجسيمات لا يكونون طبيعيون؛ إن لم يكونوا طموحين.
And the aim of particle physics is to understand
والهدف من فيزياء الجسيمات هو فهم
what everything's made of, and how everything sticks together.
مكونات صناعة كل الأشياء، وكيف أن كل الأشياء ملتصقة معاً.
And by everything I mean, of course,
و بـ "كل الأشياء" أقصد، بالطبع،
me and you, the Earth, the Sun,
أنا و أنتم، الأرض، الشمس،
the 100 billion suns in our galaxy
و المائة مليار شمس في مجرتنا
and the 100 billion galaxies
و المائة مليار مجرة
in the observable universe.
الممكن ملاحظتها بالكون.
Absolutely everything.
كل شيء على الإطلاق.
Now you might say, "Well, OK, but why not just look at it?
الآن يمكنكم القول : "حسناً، حسناً، ولكن لماذا لا ننظر فقط في ذلك؟
You know? If you want to know what I'm made of, let's look at me."
هل تعلم؟ إذا كنت تريد أن تعرف مما أنا مصنوع، دعونا ننظر إلي."
Well, we found that as you look back in time,
حسناً، وجدنا بالنظر إلى الوراء في الزمن،
the universe gets hotter and hotter,
الكون كان أكثر و أكثر سخونة،
denser and denser, and simpler and simpler.
أكثر وأكثر كثافة، وأكثر وأكثر بساطة.
Now, there's no real reason I'm aware of for that,
الآن، لا يوجد أى سبب حقيقي لإدراكى ذلك،
but that seems to be the case.
ولكن يبدو أن هذا هو الحال.
So, way back in the early times of the universe,
لذلك، بالعودة في أوقات مبكرة من الكون،
we believe it was very simple and understandable.
نعتقد أنها كانت بسيطة جداً و قابلة للفهم.
All this complexity, all the way to these wonderful things --
كل هذا التعقيد، وصولاً إلى هذه الأشياء الرائعة --
human brains -- are a property of an old
مخ الإنسان -- هو ملك لأقدم
and cold and complicated universe.
وأبرد كون معقد.
Back at the start, in the first billionth of a second,
بالعودة للبداية، في أول مليار من الثوانى،
we believe, or we've observed, it was very simple.
نعتقد، أو قد لاحظنا، إنه كان في غاية البساطة.
It's almost like ...
إنها تقريباً مثل...
imagine a snowflake in your hand,
تخيل رقاقة ثلج في يدك،
and you look at it, and it's an incredibly complicated,
ونظرت إليها، وإنها معقدة إلى حد لا يصدق،
beautiful object. But as you heat it up,
كائن جميل. ولكن بتسخينها،
it'll melt into a pool of water,
ستذوب إلى بركة من الماء،
and you would be able to see that, actually, it was just made
وستكون قادراً على رؤية ذلك؛ في الواقع كان فقط مكوناً
of H20, water.
من H2O، ماء.
So it's in that same sense that we look back in time
إذاً الأمر بالفهم نفسه أن ننظر إلى الوراء في الزمن
to understand what the universe is made of.
لفهم مما هو مصنوع هذا الكون.
And, as of today, it's made of these things.
وللوقت الحاضر، فهو مصنوع من هذه الأشياء.
Just 12 particles of matter,
فقط 12 جزيئ من المادة.
stuck together by four forces of nature.
ملتصقة معاً بأربع قوى من الطبيعة.
The quarks, these pink things, are the things that make up protons and neutrons
الكواركات، هذه الأشياء الوردية، هي الأشياء التي تشكل البروتونات والنيوترونات
that make up the atomic nuclei in your body.
التي تشكل الأنوية الذرية في جسمك.
The electron -- the thing that goes around
الإلكترون -- الشيء الذي يدور حول
the atomic nucleus --
نواة الذرة --
held around in orbit, by the way, by the electromagnetic force
مقيد في مدار، بالمناسبة، عن طريق القوة الكهرومغناطيسية
that's carried by this thing, the photon.
المنقولة عن طريق هذا الشيء، الفوتون.
The quarks are stuck together by other things called gluons.
والكواركات ملتصقة معاً بواسطة أشياء أخرى تسمى الغلونات.
And these guys, here, they're the weak nuclear force,
وهؤلاء الرفاق هنا، هم أضعف قوة بالنواة،
probably the least familiar.
ربما الأقل إلفةً.
But, without it, the sun wouldn't shine.
ولكن من دونهم لن تسطع الشمس.
And when the sun shines, you get copious quantities
وعندما تسطع الشمس، يمكنك الحصول على كميات وفيرة
of these things, called neutrinos, pouring out.
من هذه الأشياء تسمى النيوترينوات المنهمرة.
Actually, if you just look at your thumbnail --
في الواقع، إذا ألقيت مجرد نظرة على ظفر إبهامك --
about a square centimeter --
حوالي سنتيمتر مربع -- هناك حوالي
there are something like 60 billion neutrinos per second
هناك حوالي 60 مليار نيوترينوات في الثانية الواحدة
from the sun, passing
من الشمس، تسقط
through every square centimeter of your body.
على كل سنتيمتر مربع من جسمك.
But you don't feel them, because the weak force
ولكنك لا تشعر بهم وذلك لأن تسميتهم بالقوة الضعيفة
is correctly named --
تسمية صحيحة تماماً.
very short range and very weak,
مدى قصير للغاية وضعيف جداً،
so they just fly through you.
لذلك فهي فقط تمر من خلالك.
And these particles have been discovered
وهذه الجزيئات تم إكتشافها
over the last century, pretty much.
على مدى القرن الماضي، إلى حد كبير.
The first one, the electron, was discovered in 1897,
أول واحد، الإلكترون، اكتشف في عام 1897،
and the last one, this thing called the tau neutrino,
و آخر واحد، هذا الشيء يسمى تاو نيوترينو،
in the year 2000. Actually just --
في عام 2000. في الواقع أعلى --
I was going to say, just up the road in Chicago. I know it's a big country,
كنت أريد أن أقول، أعلى الطريق في "شيكاغو". وأنا أعلم أنه بلد كبير،
America, isn't it?
أمريكا، أليس كذلك؟
Just up the road.
أعلى الطريق.
Relative to the universe, it's just up the road.
نسبة إلى الكون، هو أعلى الطريق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, this thing was discovered in the year 2000,
إذاً، تم إكتشاف هذا الشيء في عام 2000،
so it's a relatively recent picture.
لذا فهي صورة حديثة نسبياً.
One of the wonderful things, actually, I find,
أحد الأشياء الرائعة، في الواقع، التي أجدها،
is that we've discovered any of them, when you realize how tiny they are.
هو عثورنا على أي واحد منهم، عندما تدرك كيف أنها صغيرة.
You know, they're a step in size
كما تعلمون، إنهم خطوة بالقياس
from the entire observable universe.
من الكون كله الذي يمكن ملاحظته.
So, 100 billion galaxies,
إذاً 100 مليار مجرة،
13.7 billion light years away --
13.7 مليار سنة ضوئية بعيداً --
a step in size from that to Monterey, actually,
خطوة بالقياس عن تلك إلى مدينة "مونتيرى"، في الواقع،
is about the same as from Monterey to these things.
هو الأمر نفسه كما من مدينة "مونتيرى" لهذه الأشياء.
Absolutely, exquisitely minute,
أنها دقيقة بشكل رائع، بكل معنى الكلمة.
and yet we've discovered pretty much the full set.
و رغم ذلك، فقد اكتشفنا تقريبا" المجموعة كلها.
So, one of my most illustrious forebears
إذاً، واحد من اكثر اسلافى لمعانا".
at Manchester University, Ernest Rutherford,
فى جامعة مانشستر, أرنست راذرفورد.
discoverer of the atomic nucleus,
مكتشف نواة الذرة،
once said, "All science is either physics
قال ذات مرة، "كل العلوم هى إما فيزياء
or stamp collecting."
او جمع طوابع."
Now, I don't think he meant to insult
حسنا، انا لا اعتقد انه قد قصد اهانة
the rest of science,
باقى العلوم،
although he was from New Zealand, so it's possible.
على الرغم من انه كان من نيوزيلندا، لذا فهذا ممكن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But what he meant was that what we've done, really,
لكن ما قصده هو ان ما قمنا به، فى الواقع
is stamp collect there.
هو جمع طوابع من هناك--
OK, we've discovered the particles,
حسنا، لقد اكتشفنا الجزيئات،
but unless you understand the underlying
لكن ما لم تفهم السبب
reason for that pattern -- you know, why it's built the way it is --
الخفى لذلك النمط -- تعرفون، لماذا بنيت كما هى --
really you've done stamp collecting. You haven't done science.
فانتم فى الواقع قد قمتم بجمع الطوابع -- لم تمارسوا العلم.
Fortunately, we have
لحسن الحظ ، لدينا
probably one of the greatest scientific achievements of the twentieth century
ربما واحد من اكبر الانجازات العلمية للقرن ال20
that underpins that pattern.
الذى يدعم هذا النمط.
It's the Newton's laws, if you want,
هو قانون نيوتن، اذا اردتم
of particle physics.
لفيزياء الجسيم.
It's called the standard model -- beautifully simple mathematical equation.
اسمه "النموذج القياسى" -- معادلة رياضية بسيطة
You could stick it on the front of a T-shirt,
يمكنكم وضعها على ،t-shirt
which is always the sign of elegance.
و ذلك دائما علامة الاناقة
This is it.
ها هو.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I've been a little disingenuous, because I've expanded it out
لقد كنت مخادعا" قليلا، لأنى قد مددته
in all its gory detail.
مع كل تفاصيله العنيفة.
This equation, though, allows you to calculate everything --
هذة المعدلة، رغم ذلك، تسمح لك بحساب كل شيء --
other than gravity -- that happens in the universe.
ما عدا الجاذبية -- يحدث فى الكون.
So, you want to know why the sky is blue, why atomic nuclei stick together --
فاذا اردت ان تعرف لماذا السماء زرقاء، لماذا تلتصق انوية الذرة مع بعضها --
in principle, you've got a big enough computer --
فى المبدأ، لديك كمبيوتر كبير كفاية --
why DNA is the shape it is.
لماذا الحمض النووى له الشكل الذى هو عليه.
In principle, you should be able to calculate it from that equation.
فى المبدأ، ينبغى عليك ان تكون قادرا على حساب ذلك من هذه المعادلة.
But there's a problem.
و لكن هناك مشكلة.
Can anyone see what it is?
هل يستطيع احد ان يرى ما هى؟
A bottle of champagne for anyone that tells me.
زجاجة شمبانبا لأى شخص يخبرنى.
I'll make it easier, actually, by blowing one of the lines up.
سوف اسهل الامر، فى الحقيقة ، بتكبير احد الخطوط.
Basically, each of these terms
فى الاساس، كل واحد من هذه المصطلحات
refers to some of the particles.
يشير الى بعض الجسيمات
So those Ws there refer to the Ws, and how they stick together.
فحروف الـ W تشير الى الـ Ws، و كيف تلتصق ببعضها.
These carriers of the weak force, the Zs, the same.
و حاملات القوة الضعيفة, حروف الـ Z، بالمثل.
But there's an extra symbol in this equation: H.
و لكن هناك رمز اضافى فى هذه المعادلة: H
Right, H.
صحيح، H
H stands for Higgs particle.
H تعبر عن جسيم هيجز.
Higgs particles have not been discovered.
لم يتم اكتشاف جسيمات هيجز .
But they're necessary: they're necessary
و لكنها ضرورية -- هى ضرورية
to make that mathematics work.
لتجعل هذه الرياضيات تعمل.
So all the exquisitely detailed calculations we can do
لذا فكل الحسابات المفصلة بشكل رائع التى يمكننا القيام بها
with that wonderful equation
بواسطة هذه المعادلة الخلابة
wouldn't be possible without an extra bit.
لن تكون ممكنة من دون جزء إضافي.
So it's a prediction:
لذا فهذا تنبؤ --
a prediction of a new particle.
تنبؤ بجسيم جديد.
What does it do?
ماذا يفعل؟
Well, we had a long time to come up with good analogies.
حسنا، كان لدينا وقت طويل للتوصل الى تشبيهات جيدة.
And back in the 1980s, when we wanted the money
و سابقا فى الثمانينات، عندما اردنا المال
for the LHC from the U.K. government,
من اجل مصادم الجسيمات العملاق من الحكومة البريطانية،
Margaret Thatcher, at the time, said,
قالت مارغريت تاتشر فى ذاك الوقت،
"If you guys can explain, in language
"اذا استطعتم ان تشرحوا، فى لغة
a politician can understand,
يستطيع سياسى ان يفهمها،
what the hell it is that you're doing, you can have the money.
ما الذى تفعلونه، يمكنكم الحصول على المال
I want to know what this Higgs particle does."
أريد ان اعرف ما الذى يفعله جسيم هيجز ذلك
And we came up with this analogy, and it seemed to work.
و قد توصلنا الى هذا التشبيه و يبدو انه يعمل
Well, what the Higgs does is, it gives mass to the fundamental particles.
حسنا، الذى يفعله هيجز هو انه يعطى كتلة للجسيمات الاساسية
And the picture is that the whole universe --
و الصورة هى ان الكون كله
and that doesn't mean just space, it means me as well, and inside you --
وهذا لا يعنى فقط الفضاء، هذا يعنى انا ايضا، و بداخلك --
the whole universe is full of something called a Higgs field.
الكون كله مليء بشيء يسمى حقل هيجز.
Higgs particles, if you will.
جسيمات هيجز، اذا اردتم.
The analogy is that these people in a room
التشبيه هو ان هؤلاء الناس فى غرفة
are the Higgs particles.
هم جسيمات هيجز.
Now when a particle moves through the universe,
الان عندما يتحرك جسيم عبر الكون،
it can interact with these Higgs particles.
يمكنه التفاعل مع جسيمات هيجز تلك.
But imagine someone who's not very popular moves through the room.
و لكن تخيل شخص ليست له شعبية كبيرة يتحرك عبر الغرفة.
Then everyone ignores them. They can just pass through the room very quickly,
عندها يتجاهله الجميع. يمكنه ان يمر عبر الغرفة بسرعة كبيرة.
essentially at the speed of light. They're massless.
أساسا بسرعة الضوء. فهو ليست له كتلة.
And imagine someone incredibly important
و تخيل شخص مهم بشكل لا يصدق
and popular and intelligent
و له شعبية كبيرة و ذكى
walks into the room.
يدخل الغرفة.
They're surrounded by people, and their passage through the room is impeded.
سوف يحيط به الناس، و مروره عبر الغرفة تتم اعاقته.
It's almost like they get heavy. They get massive.
تقريبا كأنه يصبح اثقل. تزداد كتلته.
And that's exactly the way the Higgs mechanism works.
و هكذا بالضبط تعمل تقنية هيجز.
The picture is that the electrons and the quarks
الصورة هى ان الالكترونات و الكواركات
in your body and in the universe that we see around us
فى جسمك و فى الكون الذى نراه من حولنا
are heavy, in a sense, and massive,
ثقيلة، بمعنى، و كبيرة الكتلة،
because they're surrounded by Higgs particles.
لأنها محاطة بجسيمات هيجز.
They're interacting with the Higgs field.
فهى تتفاعل مع حقل هيجز.
If that picture's true,
اذا كانت هذه الصورة صحيحة،
then we have to discover those Higgs particles at the LHC.
فعلينا ان نكتشف جسيمات هيجز تلك فى مصادم الجسيمات العملاق.
If it's not true -- because it's quite a convoluted mechanism,
و اذا لم تكن صحيحة -- لأنه آلية معقدة الى حد بعيد،
although it's the simplest we've been able to think of --
على الرغم من انها ابسط ما امكننا ان نفكر فيه --
then whatever does the job of the Higgs particles
فأيا كان ما تفعله وظيفة جسيمات هيجز
we know have to turn up
علينا الان ان نظهره
at the LHC.
فى مصادم الجسيمات العملاق.
So, that's one of the prime reasons we built this giant machine.
و هذا واحد من الاسباب الاولية التى جعلتنا نبنى تلك الألة العملاقة.
I'm glad you recognize Margaret Thatcher.
انا سعيد انكم تعرفتم علي مارغريت تاتشر.
Actually, I thought about making it more culturally relevant, but --
فى الحقيقة، لقد فكرت فى ان اجعل هذا اكثر صلة ثقافيا"، لكن --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
anyway.
على أي حال.
So that's one thing.
اذا" هذا شيء واحد.
That's essentially a guarantee of what the LHC will find.
هذا فى الأساس ضمانة لما سوف يجده مصادم الجسيمات العملاق.
There are many other things. You've heard
توجد أشياء اخرى كثيرة. انتم عرفتم
many of the big problems in particle physics.
الكثير من المعضلات فى فيزياء الجسيمات.
One of them you heard about: dark matter, dark energy.
واحدة منهم سمعتم عنها: المادة المعتمة، الطاقة المعتمة.
There's another issue,
هناك قضية اخرى،
which is that the forces in nature -- it's quite beautiful, actually --
و هى ان القوى فى الطبيعة -- هذا جميل جدا" فى الحقيقة --
seem, as you go back in time,
يبدو، بينما تعود بالزمن،
they seem to change in strength.
يبدو انها تتغير فى شدتها.
Well, they do change in strength.
حسنا، هى تتغير فى شدتها بالفعل.
So, the electromagnetic force, the force that holds us together,
اذا" القوة الكهرومغناطيسية، القوة التى تبقينا متماسكين,
gets stronger as you go to higher temperatures.
تشتد بينما تتحرك الى درجات حرارة اعلى.
The strong force, the strong nuclear force, which sticks nuclei together,
القوة الشديدة، القوة النووية الشديدة، التى تلصق النوى ببعضها،
gets weaker. And what you see is the standard model --
تضعف. و ما تراه فى النموذج القياسي --
you can calculate how these change -- is the forces,
يمكنك ان تحسب كيف تتغير -- هو القوى --
the three forces, other than gravity,
القوى الثلاث، غير الجاذبية --
almost seem to come together at one point.
يبدو تقريبا انها تتلاقى فى نقطة واحدة.
It's almost as if there was one beautiful
يبدو تقريبا و كأن كان هناك نوع جميل
kind of super-force, back at the beginning of time.
من القوة العظمى، قديما عند بداية الزمن.
But they just miss.
و لكنها تخفق.
Now there's a theory called super-symmetry,
الان هناك نظرية اسمها التناظر الفائق،
which doubles the number of particles in the standard model,
و هى تضاعف عدد الجسيمات فى النموذج القياسي.
which, at first sight, doesn't sound like a simplification.
و الذى، لأول وهلة، لا يبدو كأنه تبسيط.
But actually, with this theory,
و لكن فى الحقيقة، بواسطة هذه النظرية،
we find that the forces of nature
نجد ان قوى الطبيعة
do seem to unify together, back at the Big Bang --
تبدو انها تتحد مع بعضها، قديما عند الانفجار العظيم.
absolutely beautiful prophecy. The model wasn't built to do that,
نبؤة رائعة بحق. ان النموذج لم يُبنى ليفعل ذلك،
but it seems to do it.
و لكن يبدو انه يفعله.
Also, those super-symmetric particles
ايضا، تلك الجسيمات الفائقة التناظر
are very strong candidates for the dark matter.
هى مرشح قوى ان تكون المادة المعتمة.
So a very compelling theory
اذا" نظرية تفرض نفسها بشدة
that's really mainstream physics.
و هى فى الحقيقة تعميم الفيزياء.
And if I was to put money on it, I would put money on --
و اذا كنت سأضع المال فيها، لكنت وضعت المال --
in a very unscientific way -- that
بطريقة غير علمية اطلاقا" -- أن
that these things would also crop up at the LHC.
أن هذه الاشياء ستظهر فى مصادم الجسيمات العملاق.
Many other things that the LHC could discover.
أشياء اخرى كثيرة يمكن ان يكتشفها مصادم الجسيمات العملاق.
But in the last few minutes, I just want to give you
و لكن فى الدقائق الأخيرة القليلة، اريد ان اعطيكم
a different perspective
منظور مختلف
of what I think -- what particle physics
لما اعتقد -- ما تعنيه لى فى الحقيقة
really means to me -- particle physics and cosmology.
فيزياء الجسيمات -- فيزياء الجسيمات و علم الكونيات.
And that's that I think it's given us a wonderful
و هو انى اعتقد انها اعطتنا سرد
narrative -- almost a creation story,
رائع -- تقريبا قصة خلق،
if you'd like -- about the universe,
اذا اردتم -- عن الكون،
from modern science over the last few decades.
من العلم الحديث على مدار العقود القليلة الأخيرة.
And I'd say that it deserves,
و استطيع ان اقول انها تستحق،
in the spirit of Wade Davis' talk,
فى روح حديث وايد دافيس،
to be at least put up there with these wonderful creation stories
على الأقل ان توضع هناك فى الأعلى مع قصص الخلق الرائعة تلك
of the peoples of the high Andes and the frozen north.
للناس من جبال الأنديز العالية و الشمال المتجمد.
This is a creation story, I think, equally as wonderful.
هذه قصة خلق، اعتقد انها رائعة بنفس القدر.
The story goes like this: we know that
القصة هى كالتالى: نحن نعلم ان
the universe began 13.7 billion years ago,
الكون إبتدأ منذ 13.7 مليار سنة مضت،
in an immensely hot, dense state,
فى حالة شديدة الحرارة و الكثافة،
much smaller than a single atom.
اصغر بكثير من ذرة واحدة.
It began to expand about
و ابتدأ يتمدد حوالى
a million, billion, billion, billion billionth
واحد على مليون من مليار مليار مليار من جزء من المليار من
of a second -- I think I got that right -- after the Big Bang.
من الثانية -- اعتقد انى اصبت فى ذلك -- بعد الإنفجار العظيم.
Gravity separated away from the other forces.
انفصلت الجاذبية بعيدا" عن القوى الأخرى.
The universe then underwent
و خضع الكون
an exponential expansion called inflation.
لتمدد أسى يسمى التضخم.
In about the first billionth of a second or so,
فى حوالى اول بليون من الثانية تقريبا،
the Higgs field kicked in, and the quarks
بدأ حقل هيجز فى الظهور، و الكواركات
and the gluons and the electrons
و الغلونات و الإلكترونات
that make us up got mass.
التى تكوننا اكتسبت كتلة.
The universe continued to expand and cool.
و استمر الكون فى التمدد و تناقص درجة حرارته.
After about a few minutes,
و بعد دقائق قليلة،
there was hydrogen and helium in the universe. That's all.
وجد الهيدروجين و الهيليوم فى الكون. هذا كل شيء.
The universe was about 75 percent hydrogen,
كان الكون حوالى 75 بالمائة هيدروجين،
25 percent helium. It still is today.
25 بالمائة هيليوم. و هو لا يزال هكذا اليوم.
It continued to expand
و استمر فى التمدد
about 300 million years.
حوالى 300 مليون عام.
Then light began to travel through the universe.
ثم بدأ الضوء فى السفر عبر الكون.
It was big enough to be transparent to light,
كان كبيرا كفاية ليكون ضوءا" شفافا"،
and that's what we see in the cosmic microwave background
و هذا ما نراه فى خلفية الكون من الموجات الصغرى
that George Smoot described
و الذى وصفه جورج سمووت
as looking at the face of God.
كأنه النظر الى وجه الله.
After about 400 million years, the first stars formed,
بعد حوالى 400 مليون عام، تشكلت اوائل النجوم،
and that hydrogen, that helium, then began to cook
و هذا الهيدروجين، هذا الهيليوم، بدأت عندها بالتشكل
into the heavier elements.
الى عناصر اثقل،
So the elements of life --
اذا" عناصر الحياة --
carbon, and oxygen and iron,
الكربون، و الأكسجين و الحديد،
all the elements that we need to make us up --
جميع العناصر التى نحتاجها لتكوننا --
were cooked in those first generations of stars,
تم تشكيلها فى هذه الأجيال الأولى من النجوم،
which then ran out of fuel, exploded,
و التى عندها نفد منها الوقود، و انفجرت،
threw those elements back into the universe.
رمت هذه العناصر الى الكون مرة اخرى.
They then re-collapsed into another generation
ثم تجمعت مرة اخرى لتكون جيل جديد
of stars and planets.
من النجوم و الكواكب.
And on some of those planets, the oxygen, which had been created
و على بعض هذه الكواكب، الأكسجين الذى تم خلقه
in that first generation of stars, could fuse with hydrogen
فى هذا الجيل الأول من النجوم امكنه ان يندمج مع الهيدروجين
to form water, liquid water on the surface.
ليكون الماء، الماء السائل على السطح.
On at least one, and maybe only one of those planets,
على واحد على الأقل، و على واحد فقط على الأرجح من هذه الكواكب،
primitive life evolved,
تطورت الحياة البدائية،
which evolved over millions of years into
و التى تطورت على مدى ملايين السنين الى
things that walked upright and left footprints
اشياء سارت منتصبة و تركت أثار أقدام
about three and a half million years ago in the mud flats of Tanzania,
منذ حوالى ثلاثة ملايين سنة و نصف مضت فى سهول الطين فى تنزانيا،
and eventually
و أخيرا"
left a footprint on another world.
تركت أثر قدم على عالم أخر.
And built this civilization,
و بنت هذة الحضارة،
this wonderful picture,
هذه الصورة الخلابة،
that turned the darkness into light,
التى حولت الظلام الى نور،
and you can see the civilization from space.
و يمكنك ان ترى الحضارة من الفضاء.
As one of my great heroes, Carl Sagan, said,
و كما قال واحد من ابطالى العظماء، كارل ساجان،
these are the things -- and actually, not only these,
هذه هى الأشياء -- و فى الحقيقة ليس فقط هذه الأشياء،
but I was looking around -- these are the things,
و لكنى كنت انظر حولى -- هذه هى الأشياء،
like Saturn V rockets, and Sputnik,
مثل صواريخ ساتورنV ، و سبوتنيك،
and DNA, and literature and science --
و الحمض النووى، و الأدب و العلوم --
these are the things that hydrogen atoms do
هذه هى الأشياء التى تفعلها ذرات الهيدروجين
when given 13.7 billion years.
عندما تعطى 13.7 مليار عام.
Absolutely remarkable.
قطعا" جدير بالملاحظة.
And, the laws of physics. Right?
و قوانين الفيزياء، صحيح؟
So, the right laws of physics --
اذا"، القوانين الصحيحة للفيزياء --
they're beautifully balanced.
متوازنة بشكل جميل.
If the weak force had been a little bit different,
اذا كانت القوة الضعيفة مختلفة قليلا"،
then carbon and oxygen wouldn't be stable
لم يكن الكربون و الأكسجين ليكونا مستقرين
inside the hearts of stars,
فى داخل قلوب النجوم،
and there would be none of that in the universe.
و لم يكن ليكون أى من هذا فى الكون.
And I think that's
و أعتقد أن هذه
a wonderful and significant story.
قصة رائعة و ذات مغزى.
50 years ago, I couldn't have told that story,
قبل 50 عاما" لم اكن لأستطيع رواية هذه القصة،
because we didn't know it.
لأننا لم نكن نعرفها.
It makes me really feel that
و هى تجعلنى فعلا" اشعر أن
that civilization --
هذه الحضارة --
which, as I say, if you believe
و التى ، كما اقول، اذا صدقتم
the scientific creation story,
قصة الخلق العلمية،
has emerged purely as a result of the laws of physics,
قد برزت ببساطة كنتيجة لقوانين الفيزياء،
and a few hydrogen atoms --
و بعض ذرات الهيدروجين --
then I think, to me anyway,
و عندها اعتقد، لنفسى على أى حال،
it makes me feel incredibly valuable.
انها تجعلنى اشعر بأنى ذو قيمة جيدة تجاه نفسى .
So that's the LHC.
اذا هذا هو مصادم الجسيمات العملاق.
The LHC is certainly, when it turns on in summer,
ان مصادم الجسيمات العملاق هو حقا، عندما يعمل الصيف القادم،
going to write the next chapter of that book.
سوف يكتب الفصل التالى فى هذا الكتاب.
And I'm certainly looking forward with
و انا بالفعل اتطلع
immense excitement to it being turned on.
بإثارة بالغة لأن يعمل.
Thanks.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)